<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="funct.css" type="text/css"?>
<?xm-well_formed path="funct.dtd"?>
<slides>
 <lang>en</lang>
  <addtranscript/>
  <noslidenumbers/>
  <footer>
    <a href="https://illinois.edu">
      <img src="..\images\block-i.png"
      alt="University of Illinois"/>
    </a>
    Copyright &#169; 2021 University of Illinois
  </footer>

  <title>Keyboard Navigation and Focus Styling</title>
  <person>
    <name>Jon Gunderson</name>
    <desc href="http://disability.illinois.edu">Disability Resources and Educational Services</desc>
    <desc href="http://illinois.edu">University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</desc>
    <desc href="mailto:jongund@illinois.edu">E-mail Jon Gunderson</desc>
  </person>

  <person>
    <name>Lori Lane</name>
    <desc href="http://disability.illinois.edu">Disability Resources and Educational Services</desc>
    <desc href="http://illinois.edu">University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</desc>
    <desc href="mailto:lorilane@illinois.edu">E-mail Lori Lane</desc>
  </person>


  <stylesheet media="screen">../css/bootstrap.min.css</stylesheet>
  <stylesheet media="screen">../css/bootstrap-theme.min.css</stylesheet>
  <stylesheet media="screen">../css/bootstrap-accessibility.css</stylesheet>
  <stylesheet media="screen">../css/html-slides.css</stylesheet>

  <script>../js/jquery-2.1.1.min.js</script>
  <script>../js/bootstrap.min.js</script>
  <script>../js/bootstrap-accessibility.min.js</script>
  <script>../js/html-slides.js</script>

  <slide>
    <title>Learning Objectives</title>
    <contents>
      <ol>
        <li>All functionalities are operable by the keyboard.</li>
        <li>Tab key sequential navigation in web browsers.</li>
        <li>Visual focus styling.</li>
        <li>Bypass blocks of repetitive content.</li>
        <li>Custom widgets and menus.</li>
        <li>Keyboard related requirements of the W3C <a href="https://w3.org/TR/WCAG">Web Content Accessibility Guidelines</a>.</li>
      </ol>
      <script type="text/javascript">
        slideShowURL()
      </script>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Welcome to the web accessibility concepts course, this session you will be learning about the importance of keyboard accessibility requirements.

      Keyboard navigation is the bedrock of all software and web accessibility guidelines including the W3C Web Content Accessibility Guidelines that us used as the international standard for web accessibility laws.

      Keyboard support includes being able to both operate a web page using only the keyboard and styling the focus so people can perceive the location on the page with keyboard focus.

      Keyboard support is often misunderstood and ignored in designing online resources, since most designs and design tools focus on the dominate modes of interaction of using a mouse pointer or by touching a screen.

      Many people with disabilities though cannot use mouse or touch devices because they do not have the physical capabilities to move and operate a mouse, or the ability to press their finger on a touch screen.  People with visual impairment find it difficult or often impossible to track the location of the pointer or perceive where to touch on a screen.

      The objectives of this session is to introduce important concepts of keyboard support, which include:

      1. Sequential <kbd>Tab</kbd> keyboard navigation in browsers.

      2. Visual focus styling of the content of the page with focus.

      3. The ability to bypass blocks of repetitive content on web pages to get the main content.

      4. Keyboard interaction with menus and custom web widgets.

      5. All functionalities are operable through the keyboard.

      6. W3C Web Content Accessibility Guideline for keyboard accessibility.

    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Sequential Navigation: Using the <kbd>TAB</kbd> key</title>
    <contents>
      <table class="table table-striped" aria-label="Sequential navigation keys">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Key</th>
            <th>Description</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <kbd>tab</kbd>
            </td>
            <td>
              Moves focus to the <em>next</em> interactive element on a web page.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <kbd>shift+tab</kbd>
            </td>
            <td>
              Moves focus to the <em>previous</em> interactive element on a web page.
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>

      <h2>Accessibility Requirements</h2>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Predictable:</strong> Keyboard navigation should be easy to predict and follow, typically starting at the top left corner of the web page and moving from left to right and then from top to bottom.</li>
        <li><strong>Perceivable:</strong> An important part of keyboard navigation is identifying the location of keyboard focus on the page.</li>
        <li><strong>Operable:</strong> All the interactive elements on the page, including custom widgets should be part of the tab sequence of the page.</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Needs to be completed.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Sequential Navigation: Links and Form Controls</title>
    <contents>
      <table class="table table-striped" aria-label="Interactive elements part of tab sequence">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Element</th>
            <th>Description</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>
              Links
            </td>
            <td>
              <ul>
                <li>
                  Links (e.g. <code>a</code> elements) are the foundation of how the web works, allowing people to move easily between web pages by clicking on links.
                </li>
                <li>
                  Any link with an <code>href</code> attribute to  URL becomes part of the tab sequence of a web page.
                </li>
                <li>
                  <strong>Common Problem:</strong> Some web sites do not always use the <code>href</code> attribute to provide links to other pages.  They use something called "events" instead of the <code>href</code> attribute, in this case links often will not be part of the tab sequence and not be accessible.
                </li>
              </ul>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              Form Controls
            </td>
            <td>
              <ul>
                <li>
                  Buttons, radio button groups, checkboxes, text boxes, select and text area are some of the form controls found on web pages and by default are part of the tab sequence of the web page.
                </li>
                <li>
                  <strong>Common Problem:</strong> Some web sites use custom controls, instead of the standard HTML form controls to create web forms.  These custom controls often do not include markup to include them in the tab sequence of the page.
                </li>
              </ul>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Needs to be completed
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Activity 1: Practice using the keyboard using default focus styling</title>
    <contents>

      <h2>Goal</h2>
      <p>Increase awareness of keyboard navigation and default keyboard focus styling.</p>

      <h2>Procedure</h2>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="../examples/html/links-and-form-controls.html" target="_example1">Open the links and form controls example</a>.</li>
        <li>Verify the <q>Default browser focus styling</q> is selected from the <q>Keyboard Focus Styling Options</q>.</li>
        <li>Use the <kbd>Tab</kbd> and <kbd>Shift+Tab</kbd> to move focus between all the links and form controls.</li>
        <li>Repeat the procedure with at least two of the following browsers:
          <ul>
            <li>Chrome/Edge/Opera (these all the same rendering engine)</li>
            <li>Firefox</li>
            <li>Safari</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
      </ul>

      <h2>Reflection Questions</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>Where there any links or form controls that you could not access with the keyboard?</li>
        <li>What are the differences you observed in how links and form control focus are styled?</li>
        <li>Did you observe any differences between how browers style focus?</li>
      </ul>

    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Something about the first item.
      Something about the second item.
      Something about the third item.
      Something about the fourth item.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Activity 2: Practice using the keyboard when focus styling is disabled</title>
    <contents>

      <h2>Goal</h2>
      <p>Increase awareness of keyboard navigation when the default keyboard style has been disabled.  This condition often happens when a website uses a "reset" CSS stylesheet for decreasing styling incompatibilities between browsers and versions of the same browser.</p>

      <h2>Procedure</h2>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="../examples/html/links-and-form-controls.html#disabled" target="_example2">Open the links and form controls example</a>.</li>
        <li>Verify the <q>Disabled default focus styling</q> is selected from the <q>Keyboard Focus Styling Options</q>.</li>
        <li>Use the <kbd>Tab</kbd> and <kbd>Shift+Tab</kbd> to move focus between all the links and form controls.</li>
      </ul>

      <h2>Reflection Question</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>How could you tell with link or control had focus?</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Something about the first item.
      Something about the second item.
      Something about the third item.
      Something about the fourth item.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Activity 3: Practice using the keyboard when author intentially styles focus</title>
    <contents>

      <h2>Goal</h2>
      <p>Increase awareness of keyboard navigation when designers and developers intentionally style focus to be more perceivable by implementing a focus border around all form controls and in the case of radio buttons and checkboxes also including the label.</p>

      <h2>Procedure</h2>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="../examples/html/links-and-form-controls.html#author" target="_example3">Open the links and form controls example</a>.</li>
        <li>Verify the <q>Author focus styling</q> is selected from the <q>Keyboard Focus Styling Options</q>.</li>
        <li>Use the <kbd>Tab</kbd> and <kbd>Shift+Tab</kbd> to move focus between all the links and form controls.</li>
      </ul>

      <h2>Reflection Question</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>When the author intentionally styles the keyboard focus how does that change your ability to perceive keyboard focus?</li>
      </ul>

    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Something about the first item.
      Something about the second item.
      Something about the third item.
      Something about the fourth item.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Best practices in keyboard focus styling</title>
    <contents>

      <figure>
        <img src="images\focus-styling.png" alt="" align="middle"/>
        <caption>Screen shot of focus styling best practices for radio buttons</caption>
      </figure>

      <h2>Best Practices</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>Focus border of at least 2 pixels in width.</li>
        <li>Spacing of at least 2 pixels between border and control.</li>
        <li>Change background color of the control slightly.</li>
        <li>For radio buttons and checkboxes, the border should include the label.</li>
        <li>Hover styling should match focus styling.</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Something about the first item.
      Something about the second item.
      Something about the third item.
      Something about the fourth item.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Custom User Interface Elements</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>
          HTML links and form controls have accessibility built-in to them.  That is why it is always better to use them.
        </li>
        <li>
          When standard controls are not available for a specific user experience, designers and developers use HTML, CSS and Javascript to create custom user interface elements.  Common examples include:
          <ul>
            <li>Hide/Show content (e.g. Accordions)</li>
            <li>Navigation menus</li>
            <li>Date pickers</li>
            <li>Image carousels</li>
            <li>Media players</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://w3.org/TR/wai-aria">Accessible Rich Internet Applications (ARIA) specification</a> was created to describe the user interface elements to users of assistive technologies.
        </li>
        <li>The <a href="https://w3c.github.io/aria-practices/">ARIA Authoring Practices</a> is designed to help designers and developers learn how to use ARIA to describe the interaction features to assistive technologies.
        </li>
        <li>
          People not familiar with the coding of web technologies cannot really tell the differences between standard and custom user interface elements.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Activity 4: Practice using the keyboard for custom user interface elements</title>
    <contents>

      <h2>Keyboard board accessibility of custom inerface elements</h2>

      <h2>Goal</h2>
      <p>Increase awareness of keyboard navigation when web pages use custom user interface elements like menus, hide/show content and dialog boxes.</p>

      <h2>Procedure</h2>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="../examples/html/links-and-form-controls.html#author" target="_example3">Open the FAQ example</a>.</li>
        <li>Verify the <q>Author focus styling</q> is selected from the <q>Keyboard Focus Styling Options</q>.</li>
        <li>Use the <kbd>Tab</kbd> and <kbd>Shift+Tab</kbd> to move focus between all the links and form controls.</li>
      </ul>

      <h2>Reflection Question</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>When the author intentionally styles the keyboard focus how does that change your ability to perceive keyboard focus?</li>
      </ul>

    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Something about the first item.
      Something about the second item.
      Something about the third item.
      Something about the fourth item.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Bypass blocks of content with "Skip To Main" link.</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Item 1</li>
        <li>Item 2</li>
        <li>Item 3</li>
        <li>Item 4</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Something about the first item.
      Something about the second item.
      Something about the third item.
      Something about the fourth item.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title></title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Item 1</li>
        <li>Item 2</li>
        <li>Item 3</li>
        <li>Item 4</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Something about the first item.
      Something about the second item.
      Something about the third item.
      Something about the fourth item.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title></title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Item 1</li>
        <li>Item 2</li>
        <li>Item 3</li>
        <li>Item 4</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Something about the first item.
      Something about the second item.
      Something about the third item.
      Something about the fourth item.
    </transcript>
  </slide>


  <slide>
    <title>All functionalities are operable through the keyboard.</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="https://www.blackdogchampaign.com/">Adding an item from the online menu:</a>
          <ul>
            <li>Menu items are not part of the <kbd>tab</kbd> order of the page.</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>Item 2</li>
        <li>Item 3</li>
        <li>Item 4</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Something about the first item.
      Something about the second item.
      Something about the third item.
      Something about the fourth item.
    </transcript>
  </slide>


  <slide>
    <title> W3C Web Content Accessibility Guideline for keyboard accessibility</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Item 1</li>
        <li>Item 2</li>
        <li>Item 3</li>
        <li>Item 4</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Something about the first item.
      Something about the second item.
      Something about the third item.
      Something about the fourth item.
    </transcript>
  </slide>
</slides>


